Guide to the Vera Rony Papers TAM.593
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series III. The Uprising of '34, 1928-2002; 5.96 Linear Feet in 11 manuscript boxes, 1 small half-manuscript box, 1 flat box, and 1 small box; 27 VHS; 37 audiocassettes
  - Videotape -- The Uprising of 1934, Consortium Videos, undated (Box 23, Vhs 593_0016, 593_0018)
  - Videotape -- Hard Time Productions, The Uprising of 1934, 93 Minutes, November 16, 1994 (Box 23, Vhs 593_0021)
- Series IV. Writing, 1947-2004; 7.67 Linear Feet in 17 manuscript boxes and 1 half manuscript box
  This series reflects Rony's expertise on labor and unions, especially those in the South, through her published and unpublished writing. She published various articles on civil rights and unions in the mid-late 1960s. These articles covered topics such as union organization at J. P. Stevens, the conflict between the civil rights movement and the paper workers union in Bogalusa, Louisiana; poverty and unions; the Mississippi "tent city" strike of 1966; and the changes in the civil rights and labor movements in the South. Related drafts, notes, and research materials are included here. Additionally, she published a companion piece to The Uprising of '34 in The South Carolina Review in 1994-1995. Rony wrote a number of articles on labor that were unpublished; many of these articles were presumably used for her book, "True South," a passion project which she worked on from the 1970s through her death in 2011. The book's focus was on the history of Southern "uplanders," or descendants of Scotch and Irish pioneers in the Piedmont region (Southern Virginia, East Tennessee, the Carolinas, and Northern Georgia and Alabama), and industrial development. Rony experimented with different titles for the book, including "The Roots of the Anti-Union South: A History of the Southern Textile Workers" and "The Roots of the Anti-Union South," before settling on "True South." A significant part of this collection consists of drafts, notes, manuscripts, correspondence with editors and readers, and research for this work.
  - Subseries IV.A Published, 1961-1995
    This subseries contains drafts, notes, research material, and correspondence with publishers and readers for Rony's published articles (1960s-late 1990s), and the report that she co-wrote for WDL, on racism in Southern Labor relations.
    - Racism in Southern Labor Relations Draft, with John Schulter, for WDL, 1962 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - "Labor Drives to Close the South's Open Shop" Research Materials, 1961-1965 (Box 27, Folder 2-3)
    - "Labor Drives to Close the South's Open Shop" Notes, 1963-1965 (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - "Labor Drives to Close the South's Open Shop" Various Drafts, circa 1964-1965 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - "Labor Drives to Close the South's Open Shop" Blues, Galleys, and Published Version in The Reporter, November 18, 1865 (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - "Bogalusa: The Economics of Tragedy" Research Materials, 1949-1970 (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - "Bogalusa" Notes and Outlines, circa 1964-1965 (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - "Bogalusa" Various Drafts, circa 1964-1965 (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - "Bogalusa" Galleys and Blues, 1965-1966 (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - "Bogalusa: The Economics of Tragedy," Dissent, May 6, 1966 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - "Heartbreak in Tennessee: Poor Whites and the Unions" Research Materials, 1964-1966 (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - "Heartbreak in Tennessee" Correspondence and Notes, 1965-1966 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - "Heartbreak in Tennessee" Photographs from Look Magazine, 1965 (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - "Heartbreak in Tennessee" Various Drafts, circa 1965-1966 (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - "Heartbreak in Tennessee: Poor Whites and the Unions," Dissent, March/April 1967 (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - "Sorrow Song in Black and White" Research Materials, 1965-1967 (Box 29, Folder 5-6)
    - "Sorrow Song" Notes and Correspondence, 1965-1967 (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - "Sorrow Song in Black and White," Edits and Final Version, New South, Summer 1967 (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - "Going to Memphis" Research Materials and Notes, 1966-1967 (Box 29, Folder 9)
    - "Going to Memphis" Various Drafts, circa 1968-1969 (Box 29, Folder 10)
    - "The Uprising of 1934" Research Materials, circa 1994 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - "The Uprising of 1934" Notes and Outlines, circa 1994 (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - "The Uprising of 1934," The South Carolina Review, Fall 1994/Spring 1995 (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - Subseries IV.B Unpublished, 1947-2004
    This subseries contains speeches, lectures, and various drafts and manuscripts of her unpublished book ("True South"). Additionally, there are journals, poems, and notes.
    - Cone Mills Strike Research Materials, 1952-1967 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Cone Mills Strike Notes and Drafts for Article, 1966-1967 (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - "A Note on Southern Hospitality", 1967 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - "Death in Memphis as a Parable," Chapter for Book, circa 1968 (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - Outlines, Notes, and Drafts for Labor Articles, 1973-1977 (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - Book Review, 1984 (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - Article Written with Fred Friedman, 1987-1991 (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - Outlines, Notes, and Drafts for Article on Scottish/Irish History, 1989-1992 (Box 31, Folder 8, Box 32, Folder 1)
    - The New York Times Op Ed Letter, 1992-1993 (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - Outlines, Notes, and Drafts for Articles, 1996-2000 (Box 32, Folder 3-4, Box 33, Folder 1)
    - Diaries and Poems, 1960-2003 (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - Speeches and Papers Delivered, 1973-1995 (Box 33, Folder 3-4)
    - "True South" -- Theme Statements and Outlines, 1964-2003 (Box 34, Folder 1-2)
    - "True South" -- Reader and Publisher Comments, 1977-2001 (Box 34, Folder 3)
    - "True South" -- Early Notes and Outlines, 1947-1963 (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - "True South" -- Notes and Research, 1964 (Box 34, Folder 5)
    - "True South" -- Notes, Drafts, and Outlines, 1965 (Box 35, Folder 1-2)
    - "True South" -- Notes, Drafts, and Outlines, 1966-1967 (Box 35, Folder 3)
    - "The Rise of the South's Second Peculiar Institution" Manuscript, 1968 (Box 35, Folder 4)
    - "True South" -- Notes and Bibliographies, 1968-1969 (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - "True South" Manuscript Draft, May 1969 (Box 36, Folder 2)
    - "True South" -- Notes and Drafts, 1970-1972 (Box 36, Folder 3)
    - "True South" -- Notes and Drafts, 1973-1974 (Box 36, Folder 4)
    - "True South" -- Notes and Outlines, 1975 (Box 36, Folder 5)
    - "True South" -- Notes, Drafts, and Outlines, 1976 (Box 37, Folder 1-3)
    - "True South" -- Notes, Drafts, and Outlines, 1977 (Box 37, Folder 4-5)
    - "True South" -- Notes and Drafts, 1978 (Box 38, Folder 1)
    - "True South" -- Notes and Drafts, 1979 (Box 38, Folder 2-3)
    - "True South" -- Compiled Bibliographies, 1979-1985 (Box 38, Folder 4)
    - "True South" -- Notes and Drafts, 1980 (Box 38, Folder 5, Box 39, Folder 1)
    - "True South" -- Notes, Statistics, and Drafts, 1981 (Box 39, Folder 2)
    - "True South" -- Notes and Drafts, 1982 (Box 39, Folder 3-4)
    - "True South" -- Notes and Drafts, 1983 (Box 39, Folder 5)
    - "True South" -- Notes and Drafts, 1984 (Box 40, Folder 1-2)
    - "The Roots of the Anti-Union South," Chapters 1-2, 1984 (Box 40, Folder 3)
    - "True South" -- Notes, Drafts, and Introduction, 1985 (Box 40, Folder 4)
    - "True South" -- Compiled Bibliographies, 1986-1993 (Box 40, Folder 5)
    - "The Roots of the Anti-Union South," Chapters 1-2, Incomplete, 1987 (Box 40, Folder 6)
    - "True South" -- Notes and Drafts, 1987-1988 (Box 40, Folder 7)
    - "True South" -- Notes and Statistics, 1990 (Box 41, Folder 1-2)
    - "True South" -- Notes, Drafts, and Outlines, 1991 (Box 41, Folder 3-4)
    - "True South" -- Notes and Drafts, 1992 (Box 42, Folder 1)
    - "True South" -- Notes and Drafts, 1993 (Box 42, Folder 2-3)
    - "True South" -- Notes, 1994 (Box 42, Folder 4)
    - "True South" -- Notes and Drafts, 1995 (Box 42, Folder 5-6, Box 43, Folder 1)
    - "True South" -- Various Drafts of "The Home Front" Section, circa 1995-1999 (Box 43, Folder 2)
    - "True South" -- Notes and Outlines, 1996 (Box 43, Folder 3)
    - "True South" -- Notes and Outlines, 1997 (Box 43, Folder 4)
    - "True South" -- Notes, Drafts, and Outlines, 1998 (Box 43, Folder 5)
    - "True South" -- Notes and Outlines, 1999 (Box 44, Folder 1-2)
    - "True South" -- Notes and Drafts, 2000 (Box 44, Folder 3)
    - "True South" -- Notes, Drafts, and Outlines, 2001-2004 (Box 44, Folder 4)
- Series V. Subject Files, 1904-2003; 9.19 Linear Feet in 21 manuscript boxes; 2 VHS
  This series also reflects Rony's lifelong study of labor history since it mainly contains research material on topics including the Southern textile industry and labor in the South, which were the focus of her writing, teaching, and The Uprising of '34. Most, if not all, of these materials also were used by Rony in her writing and teaching, and for the film. Materials include clippings; peer-reviewed articles; and reports, statistics, newsletters, and press releases from institutions and government bodies such as the AFL-CIO, STFU, and the Department of Labor.
  - Affirmative Action, 1975-1995 (Box 45, Folder 1)
  - AFL-CIO, 1958-2001 (Box 45, Folder 2)
  - Agricultural Unions, 1959-1977 (Box 45, Folder 3)
  - Alabama, 1937-1991 (Box 45, Folder 4-5)
  - Allen, John Earl -- "The Governor and the Strike: Eugene Talmadge and the General Textile Strike, a Thesis", 1977 (Box 45, Folder 6)
  - Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU), 1976-1993 (Box 46, Folder 1-2)
  - American Federation of Hosiery Workers, 1934 (Box 46, Folder 3-5, Box 47, Folder 1-4)
  - American Federation of Teachers, 1964 (Box 47, Folder 5)
  - American Labor Museum, circa 1983-2000 (Box 47, Folder 6)
  - American Solidarity Movement, 1984 (Box 47, Folder 7)
  - Americans for Democratic Action, 1966-1980 (Box 47, Folder 8)
  - Appalachian Region, 1935-1972 (Box 47, Folder 9)
  - Arkansas, 1964-1974 (Box 47, Folder 10)
  - Association for Union Democracy, 1987-2001 (Box 48, Folder 1)
  - Atlantic Economic Review, February 1971 (Box 48, Folder 2)
  - Bargaining, 1974-1983 (Box 48, Folder 3)
  - Bibliographies, 1960-2003 (Box 48, Folder 4)
  - Black Elected Officials, 1968 (Box 48, Folder 5)
  - Black-Jewish Relations, circa 1962-1976 (Box 48, Folder 6)
  - Black Panthers, 1970 (Box 48, Folder 7)
  - Blacks and Labor, 1960-1991 (Box 48, Folder 8)
  - Bricklayers, Masons, and Plasterers International Union, 1970 (Box 48, Folder 9)
  - British History, 1909-1978 (Box 48, Folder 10)
  - Brown Lung Disease, 1975 (Box 48, Folder 11)
  - Bureau of Labor Statistics, 1964-1976 (Box 48, Folder 12)
  - Business Week, 1976-1998 (Box 48, Folder 13)
  - B, 1985-2001 (Box 48, Folder 14)
  - Callaway Mills, 1943-1977 (Box 48, Folder 15)
  - Capitalism, 1999-2002 (Box 48, Folder 16)
  - Carolina Alliance for Fair Employment (CAFE), 1995-1997 (Box 48, Folder 17)
  - Carr, Clare O'Neill -- A Brief History of Red Hook, 2001 (Box 49, Folder 1)
  - Cash, W. J. -- The Mind of the South, 1941 (Box 49, Folder 2)
  - Censorship, 1975 (Box 49, Folder 3)
  - Charlotte, North Carolina, 1964-1997 (Box 49, Folder 4)
  - Civil Rights, 1963-2000 (Box 49, Folder 5)
  - Civil Rights Act of 1964, 1964-1966 (Box 49, Folder 6)
  - Civil Rights in the South, 1934-1995 (Box 49, Folder 7)
  - Cotton, 1934-1965 (Box 49, Folder 8)
  - The Crisis, 1975-1977 (Box 49, Folder 9)
  - C, 1976-1998 (Box 49, Folder 10)
  - Democratic Study Group, 1965 (Box 49, Folder 11)
  - Desegregation, 1961-2000 (Box 49, Folder 12)
  - D, 1976-1980 (Box 50, Folder 1)
  - Education in the South, 1965-1966 (Box 50, Folder 2)
  - Electrical Unions, 1963-1966 (Box 50, Folder 3)
  - Equal Employment Opportunity Commission, 1965-1966 (Box 50, Folder 4)
  - Family Assistance Act of 1970 (Box 50, Folder 5)
  - Federal Aid, 1965-1997 (Box 50, Folder 6)
  - Georgia, 1907-1988 (Box 50, Folder 7)
  - Globalization, 1982-2000 (Box 50, Folder 8)
  - The Great Migration, 1961 (Box 50, Folder 9)
  - Hate and Extremist Groups, 1964-1996 (Box 50, Folder 10)
  - Healthcare, 1995-2001 (Box 50, Folder 11)
  - Helfand, Judith, 1997-2000 (Box 50, Folder 12, Box 23, Vhs 593_0024)
  - H, 1966-2000 (Box 50, Folder 13)
  - In These Times, December 8-14, 1982 (Box 50, Folder 14)
  - Industrial Relations Research Association, 1977-1982 (Box 50, Folder 15)
  - Industrial Relations Research Institute, University of Wisconsin, 1958-1968 (Box 50, Folder 16)
  - Industrial Union Department (IUD), AFL-CIO, 1965-1984 (Box 50, Folder 17)
  - Industrial Worker, August 1976 (Box 50, Folder 18)
  - Industrialization in the South, 1949-1971 (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Institute for Southern Studies, 1972 (Box 51, Folder 2)
  - Institute of Industrial Relations, University of California, Berkeley, 1961-1978 (Box 51, Folder 3)
  - Institute of Labor and Industrial Relations, University of Illinois, 1933-1977 (Box 51, Folder 4)
  - International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU), 1965-1972 (Box 51, Folder 5)
  - Irons, Janet Christine -- "Testing the New Deal: The General Textile Strike of 1934", 1988 (Box 51, Folder 6)
  - I, 1983-1997 (Box 51, Folder 7)
  - Jerome Levy Economics Institute of Bard College, 1994-2001 (Box 51, Folder 8, Box 52, Folder 1)
  - Job Discrimination, 1965-1975 (Box 52, Folder 2)
  - John Herling's Labor Letter, 1966-1967 (Box 52, Folder 3)
  - Joint Economic Committee, 1976 (Box 52, Folder 4)
  - J. P. Stevens Labor Disputes, 1964-1982 (Box 52, Folder 5-7, Box 53, Folder 1)
  - Labor Analysis and Forecast, 1959-1965 (Box 53, Folder 2)
  - Labor and Politics, 1952-1965 (Box 53, Folder 3)
  - Labor and Technology, 1986 (Box 53, Folder 4)
  - Labor History, 1934-2002 (Box 53, Folder 5-6)
  - Labor in the South, 1947-1992 (Box 54, Folder 1-3)
  - Labor-Management Cooperation, 1976-1980 (Box 54, Folder 4)
  - Labor Migration, 1973 (Box 54, Folder 5)
  - Labor Programs of Study, 1964-1982 (Box 54, Folder 6)
  - Land Reform, 1972 (Box 54, Folder 7)
  - League for Industrial Democracy, 1968-1971 (Box 54, Folder 8)
  - The "Left", 1966-1998 (Box 54, Folder 9)
  - Levenson, Albert M. -- "Manpower Supply and Demand in Nassau-Suffolk, 1965-1975", 1969 (Box 55, Folder 1)
  - Lewis, John, circa 1977-1981 (Box 55, Folder 2)
  - "Let's Be Human", 1969-1984 (Box 55, Folder 3)
  - Lindqvist, Sven -- "Dig Where You Stand", 1982 (Box 55, Folder 4)
  - Louisiana, 1961-1977 (Box 55, Folder 5-6)
  - Maps, 1940-1944 (Box 55, Folder 7)
  - Marxism, undated (Box 55, Folder 8)
  - Mauelshagen, Carl and Gerald H. Davis, eds. -- Partners in the Lord's Work: The Diary of Two Moravian Missionaries in the Creek Indian Country, 1807-1813, 1969 (Box 55, Folder 9)
  - Militant Truth, 1962-1965 (Box 55, Folder 10)
  - The Mill Hunk Herald, Summer 1988 (Box 55, Folder 11)
  - Mississippi, 1961-1975 (Box 55, Folder 12)
  - Mountain Life and Work, 1976-1985 (Box 55, Folder 13-14)
  - M, 1985-1988 (Box 56, Folder 1)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), 1974-1979 (Box 56, Folder 2)
  - The Nation, 1976-2000 (Box 56, Folder 3)
  - National Labor Relations Act (NLRA), 1964-1977 (Box 56, Folder 4)
  - National Labor Relations Board (NLRB), 1964-1995 (Box 56, Folder 5-6)
  - The National Times, 1996-1997 (Box 56, Folder 7)
  - Negro Digest, February 1966 (Box 56, Folder 8)
  - The New Force, 1932 (Box 56, Folder 9)
  - New South (Concept), 1950-1988 (Box 56, Folder 10)
  - New South (Publication), 1957-1973 (Box 57, Folder 1)
  - Newsweek, 1963-1967 (Box 57, Folder 2)
  - Norma Rae, 1979-1980 (Box 57, Folder 3)
  - North Carolina, 1930-1999 (Box 57, Folder 4)
  - North Carolina -- Politics, 1958-1965 (Box 57, Folder 5)
  - Northern Textile Industry, 1917-1981 (Box 57, Folder 6)
  - N, 1979-1994 (Box 57, Folder 7)
  - Operation Dixie, 1953-1992 (Box 57, Folder 8-9)
  - Ortega y Gasset, Jos -- Man and Crisis, 1958 (Box 57, Folder 10)
  - Poetry, circa 1917-1939 (Box 58, Folder 1)
  - Populism, 1976-1977 (Box 58, Folder 2)
  - Poverty, 1964-1974 (Box 58, Folder 3)
  - Productivity, 1977-1980 (Box 58, Folder 4)
  - Progressive Labor Party (PLP), 1965 (Box 58, Folder 5)
  - Publishing, 1965-2000 (Box 58, Folder 6)
  - Quality Control, 1979-1980 (Box 58, Folder 7)
  - The Quarterly Review of Economics and Business, Winter 1969 (Box 58, Folder 8)
  - Quotes, undated (Box 58, Folder 9)
  - Racism, 1934-1994 (Box 58, Folder 10)
  - Ragan, Sam, ed. -- The New Day, 1964 (Box 58, Folder 11)
  - Rash, Ron -- "Eureka", undated (Box 58, Folder 12)
  - Reconstruction, 1904-1989 (Box 58, Folder 13)
  - Religion, 1942-1989 (Box 58, Folder 14)
  - Republican Party, 1949-1995 (Box 59, Folder 1)
  - Retirement, 1996 (Box 59, Folder 2)
  - Rieve-Pollock Foundation, 1995 (Box 59, Folder 3)
  - R. J. Reynolds, 1951-1965 (Box 59, Folder 4)
  - Socialism, 1939-1984 (Box 59, Folder 5)
  - South Carolina, 1965-1995 (Box 59, Folder 6)
  - South Today, 1970-1973 (Box 59, Folder 7)
  - Southern Exposure, 1973-1999 (Box 59, Folder 8-9)
  - Southern Mutual Help Association, 1973-1994 (Box 59, Folder 10)
  - The Southern Patriot, 1972-1976 (Box 60, Folder 1)
  - Southern Regional Council, 1959-1982 (Box 60, Folder 2)
  - Southern States -- History, 1966-1990 (Box 60, Folder 3)
  - Southern Textile Industry, 1914-1988 (Box 60, Folder 4)
  - Stetin, Sol, 1929-1999 (Box 60, Folder 5-6)
  - Stokes, Thomas L. -- Carpetbaggers of Industry, 1937 (Box 60, Folder 7)
  - Stoney, George C., 1938-1941 (Box 60, Folder 8, Box 23, Vhs 593_0023)
  - Taft-Hartley Act, 1945-1966 (Box 61, Folder 1)
  - Technological Innovations, 1979-1983 (Box 61, Folder 2)
  - Tennessee, 1961-1969 (Box 61, Folder 3-4)
  - Tennessee -- Politics, 1962-1965 (Box 61, Folder 5)
  - Texas, 1960-1997 (Box 61, Folder 6)
  - The Texas Observer, 1958-1985 (Box 61, Folder 7)
  - Textile Industry -- History, 1930-1966 (Box 62, Folder 1)
  - Textile Workers Union of American (TWUA), 1939-1990 (Box 62, Folder 2-4, Box 63, Folder 1)
  - The Toadstool, 1924-1925 (Box 63, Folder 2)
  - Tobacco Workers Union, 1964 (Box 63, Folder 3)
  - Unemployment, 1965-1984 (Box 63, Folder 4)
  - The Union for Experimenting Colleges and Universities, 1981 (Box 63, Folder 5)
  - United Auto Workers, 1965-1998 (Box 63, Folder 6)
  - United Nations Industrial Development Organization, 1973 (Box 63, Folder 7)
  - United Packinghouse Workers and the Amalgamated (UPWA), 1967 (Box 63, Folder 8)
  - United States Department of Labor, 1963-1977 (Box 63, Folder 9-10, Box 64, Folder 1)
  - United States Politics, 1962-1994 (Box 64, Folder 2)
  - United Steel Workers of America, 1951-1981 (Box 64, Folder 3)
  - United Textile Workers of America, 1934-1936 (Box 64, Folder 4)
  - Voting Rights, 1963-1982 (Box 64, Folder 5)
  - Wages, 1927-1996 (Box 64, Folder 6)
  - Watts Riots, 1965-1966 (Box 64, Folder 7)
  - White Organizing, 1967 (Box 64, Folder 8)
  - Women in the Workplace, 1972-1995 (Box 64, Folder 9)